A Guide to the Carol M. Newman Papers, 1897-1958
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Carol M. Newman Papers, 1897-1958
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1978-003
0.7 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 oversize folder
Papers of Carol M. Newman, professor of English at Virginia Tech (1903-1941) and secretary of the university's Athletic Council (1914-1939). Includes correspondence, awards and honors, Athletic Council files, speeches and essays, examination questions, and subject files on Virginia Tech, language and literature.
Newman, Carol M., (Carol Montgomery), 1879-1941
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Carol M. Newman Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1978. The European travel diary was donated to Special Collections in 1988 as part of the Carol M. Newman Jr. Papers and was moved to this collection at the time of processing.
Biographical Note
Carol Montgomery Newman, son of Thomas J. and Alda Roper Newman, was born in Wytheville, Virginia on October 29, 1879. At the age of five, Montgomery moved with his family to Bristol, Virginia. After graduating from Bristol's King College in 1897, Newman worked for a year in the local office of the Norfolk & Western Railway, then entered the University of Virginia. There, he became an instructor in English and obtained his master's degree in 1901. Newman married Caroline "Carrie" Fain (1880-1960) in 1902; the couple would have four children. That same year, Newman became an instructor of languages at St. Albans School in Radford, Virginia. He returned to the University of Virginia as an instructor in English literature and obtained his Ph.D. in 1903. That same year, Newman joined the faculty of Virginia Polytechnic Institute as an associate professor of English. In 1907, he was named professor of rhetoric and in 1915, dean of the academic department. Newman was very active in the school's extracurricular activities, serving as secretary of the athletic council from 1914 to 1939, chair of the college social committee and the YMCA advisory board, and as a member of the library committee; he was also a frequent speaker at university and local events. Carol M. Newman died in Blacksburg, Virginia on September 8, 1941, and was buried in the town's Westview Cemetery.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Virginia Tech English Professor Carol M. Newman. Within the papers are correspondence, honors and awards, Athletic Association files, speeches and essays, examination questions, and subject files on Virginia Tech, language and literature. Much of the correspondence consists of letters of recommendation written for Newman while seeking a position in Virginia Tech's Department of English. Other letters are from friends, including Albert Jay Nock; and university colleagues and officials, including John M. McBryde, Paul Barringer, Julian Burruss, Paul Derring and C. P. "Sally" Miles. Several items relate to a donation of books from the estate of George William Walker. Among the correspondence are a few letters addressed to Caroline Newman. Also relating to Virginia Tech are files maintained by Newman as secretary of the university's Athletic Council, as well as a file of general university-related materials, including newspaper clippings, drafts of public addresses, and a roster of university staff from 1872 to 1919. The collection also contains a diary maintained by Newman during a trip to Europe in 1906, a collection of Newman's honors (including the dedication of the 1917 Bugle and of Carol M. Newman Library), and drafts of essays and speeches written by Newman, some intended for a radio audience. Newman's teaching activities are represented in a collection of exam questions compiled by him, as well as reading lists and files relating to language, grammar, literature, and writers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Carol M. Newman Jr. Papers (Ms1978-004)
Separated Materials
The following item was removed from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
A Year With Va. Tech's Y.M.C.A. [Blacksburg, VA: YMCA at Virginia Tech], 1942.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1903-1958 (Box-folder 1-1)
- European travel diary, 1906 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Awards and honors, 1916-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Essays and speeches, 1927-1940 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Essays and speeches, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-5)
- Athletic Council, 1923-1930 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Athletic Council, 1931-1933, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Virginia Tech, 19l9-1922, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Exam questions, 1919-1933 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Exam questions, 1934-1941, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Language and grammar, 1908-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-11)
- Literature, poetry, and writers, 1925-1931, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Reading lists, 1930-1940, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Oversize materials, 1897-1927 (Oversize 1)
  - King's College diploma, 1897
  - Raven Society certificate, 1927